Guide to the Morgan Phelps Noyes Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Morgan Phelps Noyes Papers
1913-1972
RG 198
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(5 boxes)
Sermons, writings, and memorabilia document the life and work of prominent Presbyterian minister Morgan Phelps Noyes. Noyes was a 1914 graduate of Yale University, received an honorary D.D. from Yale in 1938, and was a member of the Yale University Corporation from 1945 to 1959. He served served churches in New York and New Jersey from 1920 to 1957 and was Associate Professor of Practical Theology at Union Theological Seminary in New York from 1945 to 1951.
Noyes, Morgan Phelps, 1891-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Merrill Mead-Fox, 2013
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Morgan Phelps Noyes was born in Warren, Pennsylvania on March 29, 1891. He graduated from Phillips Exeter Academy in 1910, from Yale University in 1914, from Union Theological Seminary in 1920, and received an M.A. from Columbia University in 1922. Noyes married Marjorie Clarke in 1926 and they had two children. He received an honorary doctorate from Yale University in 1938. He was a member of the Corporation of Yale University from 1945 to 1959. Rev. Noyes was a direct descendant of James Noyes (1640-1719), Senior Fellow of Yale University's original Board of Trustees.
Rev. Noyes was ordained in 1917 prior to his service with the YMCA in Russia. He served as Assistant Minister at the Madison Avenue Presbyterian Church in New York City from 1919 to 1920. He then served the Presbyterian Church of Dobbs Ferry, NY from 1920 to 1925, First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, NY from 1925 to 1932 and Central Presbyterian Church in Montclair, NJ from 1932 to 1957. Following his retirement he served in various interim pastorates in New Jersey and Connecticut. He was a member of the faculty at The Masters School, Dobbs Ferry from 1921 to 1925 and was Associate Professor Practical Theology at Union Theological Seminary from 1945 to 1951.
Noyes died on June 20, 1972. For additional biographical information, see Series III, Biographical Documentation.
Scope and Contents
The sermons, writings, and biographical documentation in this collection provide insight into the life and work of prominent minister and civic leader Morgan Phelps Noyes. As noted in the memorial tribute of Yale Chaplain Sidney Lovett, Noyes was a "scholar and teacher, churchman and community leader, author and preacher."
Series I, Sermons, contains typescript and printed sermons from the years 1929 to 1971. The chronologically arranged sermons are followed by undated sermons arranged by title and scriptural text.
Series II, Writings and Notes, provides a flavor of the writings Noyes published in magazines and newspapers, as well as his booklength works and prayers. Notes from his days as a Yale student and as a minister are also available.
Series III, Biographical Documentation, includes documents, clippings, certificates, and tributes to Noyes' work for the church and community. Of particular interest are a set of 44 colored glass lantern slides that document the period when Noyes was serving with the YMCA in Russia, working with the Russian and Czechoslovakian armies during World War I. The slides show everyday life, street scenes, and military personnel in Russia during this era.
Arrangement
I. Sermons, 1929-1971, no date
II. Writings and Notes, 1913-1965, no date
III. Biographical Documentation, 1918-1972, no date
Sermons, American; Noyes, Morgan Phelps, 1891-
- Sermons, 1929-1971, no date; Series I
  - Printed and typescript sermons, primarily preached at First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, including "The Reality of God" and "The Christian and his Country", 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Printed sermons preached at First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn and Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, including "This Generation Seeketh After a Sign", "Puppets or Citizens"; published sermon "Our Debt to Seamen", 1930-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Typescript sermons, including "Conforming and Transforming", "Twenty-third Psalm", 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typescript sermons, including "So I Send You", "God's New Deed"; printed sermon "Everybody Has a Hard Fight", 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed and typescript sermons, including "The Simplicity That Is In Christ (in memory of Dr. Grenfell)", "Isn't One Religion As Good As Another", 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Printed booklet: "Questions People Ask" - A series of sermons preached during the Lenten season 1947 in the Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, by The Reverend Morgan Phelps Noyes, D.D., Minister (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed and typescript sermons preached at Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, including "Does the Church Have a Man's Job", "What is Freedom For?", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Printed and typescript sermons preached at Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, including "A Sane View of One's Self", "Thanksgiving - For What?", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Printed and typescript sermons preached at Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, including " Where the Light Shines", sermon preached at Yale University ""The Goodness and Severity of God", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Printed and typescript sermons preached at Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, including "The Fact that Ends Fear", "Now Thank We All Our God", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Printed and typescript sermons preached at Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, including "Light For Our Times", "The Lord's Prayer", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Printed and typescript sermons, primarily preached at Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, including "The Golden Calf", "For an Age of Anxiety", 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Printed and typescript sermons primarily preached at Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, including "The Beatitudes", "Questions Men Asked Jesus", 1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Printed and typescript sermons primarily preached at Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, including "The Marks of Discipleship", "The Layman and the Church", 1955 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Printed and typescript sermons primarily preached at Central Presbyterian Church, Montclair, New Jersey, including "Books That Changed the World", "The Reformation Faith", 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Typescript sermons, primarily preached at First Congregational Church, Columbus, Ohio, including "The Redeeming Gospel", "I Have Found the Book", 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Printed and typescript sermons, including "His Dying - Our Living", "The Cup of the New Covenant", 1961-1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Undated sermons by title: "Can Christianity Be Practiced in Today's World" - "Freedom and Education", no date (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Undated sermons by title: "Gateways to God" - "Is Belief in God Superstition?", no date (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Undated sermons by title: "The Law of Liberty" - "Workmen Not Ashamed", no date (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Undated sermons by scriptural citation: Old Testament, no date (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Undated sermons by scriptural citation: Gospels, no date (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Undated sermons by scriptural citation: Epistles, no date (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Addendum: Typescript sermon on I. Corinthians 2:6, printed sermon "Time to Trust"; handwritten notes for sermons, 1945-1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Addendum: Printed sermons, including series on the Lord's Prayer preached at First Congregational Church, Columbus, Ohio, 1947-1960 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Writings and Notes, 1913-1965, no date; Series II
  - Typescript talks and essays, including "Religious Tolerance in a Democracy", "The Christian Family", 1940-1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Typescript talks and essays, including "Some Reflections on the Theistic Problem", "Why Doesn't the Church Take a Stand?", "The Mysticism of Thomas à Kempis", no date (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Address: "The Role of the Private Citizen in Relation to the Social Services of the State"; published book reviews by Noyes; reviews of "Preaching the Word of God" by Noyes, 1930s-ca. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Book: Henry Sloane Coffin, the Man and his Ministry (New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1964) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Reviews and publicity for Henry Sloane Coffin, the Man and his Ministry, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Letters regarding Henry Sloane Coffin, the Man and his Ministry, including from William Sloane Coffin, 1963 Jul - 1964 May (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Letters regarding Henry Sloane Coffin, the Man and his Ministry, including from Mrs. Henry Sloane Coffin, 1964 Jun - 1965 Dec, no date (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Pamphlet: Louis F. Benson, Hymnologist, published by Hymn Society of America, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Prayers, 1935-1961, no date (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Prayers, 1919-1970 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Notebook: Notes taken for Philosophy class at Yale, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 2 Notebooks: notes and quotes, 1930s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Biographical Documentation, 1918-1972, no date; Series III
  - Correspondence, including from Henry Sloane Coffin, Sidney Lovett, 1918-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - CV, biographical documents, citations and tributes, 1920-1970, no date (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Biographical newspaper clippings, 1929-1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Biographical newpaper clippings, interview with Noyes in The Christian Ministry, 1950-1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous orders of service (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Memorial service program, tributes, obituaries for Noyes, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, including of Yale Corporation, 1955-1959 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 44 lantern slides taken when Noyes was serving with the YMCA in Russia during World War I, circa 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 5)